Hi everyone. Welcome back to day number
three of our Kaggle generative AI
intensive course where we'll be
discussing generative AI agents. I hope
everybody had great fun in the last
couple of days where we were talking
about foundational models, prompt
engineering, and then also embeddings
and vector databases. Um today we have a
really exciting course for you um
walking through some really interesting
code labs where you can create your own
agents um as well as getting a Q&A with
some of our really exciting guest
speakers including folks from the Ada
team um which is baking AI assistant
features into tools like Colab as well
as the creator of NotebookLM. Um so
really excited to have you here today
and to have you tuned in. Um as an
as a reminder as a course overview um
the course that we're delivering is a
five-day generative AI intensive course
on
a
sort of all of the tools that you can
use to build models to interact with
models and to bake AI into your
applications sponsored by Google and
Kaggle. Um you're getting daily
assignments in the forms of white papers
and podcasts which explain the what and
how of how things work um as well as
accompanying code labs um that will
teach you how to how to do all of the
great things that our speakers and our
white papers are describing. Um you can
test them out in Kaggle as Kaggle
kernels or you can export the notebooks
and use them in Colab
and run them at your leisure. Um this is
really intended to help you dive deep
into learn some of the fundamental
concepts
around tech and around generative AI. Um
so as a reminder today is day number
three um where you have hopefully read
all of the white papers, interacted with
all of the folks on our Discord
channels, and also listened to to the
podcasts. Um coming up soon we're going
to have a not walk through the code labs
just in case you have any questions or
if you wanted to have somebody kind of
hold your hand um as you tackle the
great programming concepts.
And we're really hoping that that by the
end of this course, you'll be building
your own AI agents and using them to
accomplish really interesting tasks.
So with that, I'm going to turn it over
to Anant for the curriculum review and
then also our code labs for generative
AI agents. Anant, do you want to take it
over?
You might need to come off mute.
So thanks Paige.
And before I start, I'd like to give a
shout-out to Mark McDonald who had
created these Colabs. And yeah,
so
thanks for being here everyone and
welcome to our live stream. So today
I'll be walking you through the contents
of the Colab for day three AI agents,
generative AI agents to be more
specific. And so in day two and day one,
so you've seen basically how
foundational models are created, the
fundamental components, how they can be
made fast and efficient at inference
time, as well as some of the
applications and how they can be
prompted and and the various strategies
for prompting large language models. And
then you've also seen embeddings, how
embeddings represent various different
data types in compact semantic
representations which can then be
combined together with vector databases
and approximate nearest neighbor
algorithms to kind of query and manage
these embeddings at scale to build many
generative AI applications such as
retrieval augmented generation, but also
help with other applications such as
clustering, classification, and so on
and so forth. Now, building from day one
and day two, we come on to
a topic which is very important which
can you which utilize these techniques,
both LLMs and um
embeddings and data sources
vector data sources to build AI agents
and that would be the focus of this
curriculum overview and code lab
overview.
So, I hope all of you have had a chance
to go through the white paper or at
least the podcast summary of it.
So, in the first section of the white
paper we explored basically the
foundational components of what
constitutes an AI agent, specifically a
generative AI agent and the various
components being models, tools, and
orchestration layers and how these
elements interact to enable intelligent
behavior. We we can then compile these
components to build systems that are
capable of understanding the world,
making decisions, and acting upon those
decisions extending beyond the
limitations of just standalone LLM's.
Then, the second part of the white paper
dives into some of the tools that these
agents can leverage to interact with the
external world and access information
beyond their initial training data.
Some of these tools that we discussed
are called extensions, functions, and
data sources. Extensions being basically
the bridge
which kind of connects the agents with
external APIs basically facilitating
seamless execution of these API calls.
Then functions. Functions are basically
the tools which empower developers with
fine-grained control over the data flow
and system execution
basically enabling client-side
processing and data transformations.
Then data sources. And data sources
provide agents with access to structured
or unstructured data
enabling data-driven applications and
and other downstream tasks such as um
um uh, retrieval augmented generation.
Now, in the next part, we then, uh,
after seeing these various types of
tools, um, we then looked at how we can
enhance model performance for agents
using targeted learning approaches. Some
of these being in-context learning,
retrieval-based in-context learning, as
well as fine-tuning to enhance an
agent's ability to choose the right
tools and then gen- use those tools to
generate the optimal outputs for the
task at hand.
These approaches basically, um,
uh, equip agents with the specific
knowledge and adaptability needed to
excel in real-world scenarios.
Then, after all of this, um, the white
paper concludes by looking at building
agentic applications using LangChain and
Google's Vertex AI platform, which, uh,
greatly simplifies the development and
deployment of these production-grade
agentic applications and, uh, allow, uh,
allowed uh, developers to, um, uh,
refine find, uh, defi- uh, refine, uh,
the applications in an iterative fashion
and by providing the, uh, the services
which manage the complexities of
infrastructure, deployment, and
maintenance. So,
hopefully, uh, the uh, this gives a
overview for those of you who are
joining for the first time or, um, or
who have read the white paper and want
some background before our Colab. And,
um, now I'll be going into, uh, our
Colab and I'll be taking over the
screen.
So, uh,
uh, so, first Colab which you got in
your assignment today deals with
function calling with the Gemini API.
Essentially, this, uh, this Colab, um,
goes over how you can leverage Gemini's
automatic function calling to to
bi- build kind of like a conversational
chat interface with a database. In this
case,
for um
demo and learning purposes, we'll be
leveraging a local database, a SQLite
in-memory database. But, of course, um
in the real production gate
applications, you'd be leveraging
different ones.
And it's important to note this is a toy
example. So,
so don't go just using exactly the same
code in a production gate applications
as you would need a bunch of safety and
security constraints as well as other
things on top if you would like to build
a safe production gate applications.
application
So, we start off this collab with as
usual like installing the necessary
libraries.
Um
retrieving the Google AI Studio API key
through Kaggle secrets, which you've
done in first couple of days as well.
Initializing the Gemini API with that
API key and
the usual stuff.
Then,
in this
part of the collab, we create a local
SQLite database as I mentioned earlier
and add some and populate it with some
synthetic data so we have something to
play around with in order to learn how
it works.
So, in this case, we create a synthetic
table which contains product ID, product
name, and price. These are the products
which will be used which the users can
order. And then we create a staff table.
This contains information about the
staff members who'd be
kind of selling or taking orders from
the customer containing information like
their IDs and first and last names. And
then
we create finally an orders table which
contains the order ID, customer customer
name, staff ID, and product ID.
Basically, allowing a customer to place
to place an order with a with a
particular staff number staff member
and this is what um
it allows you to then we add some
synthetic data
uh into the products table. Similarly,
add synthetic uh staff information and
um
uh and order information. So, basically,
that mean this particular customer
ordered a certain product with a certain
staff member and that is what we um add
into the orders table.
Great.
Now, at this point, we have a synthetic
uh SQLite Well, it's
we have a SQLite database uh populated
with synthetic information. And now, we
shall go ahead and define some database
functions which uh
which will basically be exposed as um
uh as tools um to the um
to the um LLM in order to allow it to um
uh
use these tools to interact with the
database.
Um now, it's important to note that uh
we'll be using an
uh um
Uh so, it's it's important to note that
uh we'll be using a toy example here, uh
but it's important for the LLM in order
to um
let an LLM um understand how which which
functions or which tools to call and
what and how to convert those um
uh
these functions, like how to convert the
natural language text that the user is
sending, how to convert it to a query
and the parameters for the queries and
the function parameters. It's important
that you need to
define often need to define the what
each parameter stands for, what does it
mean, the input parameters, and how it
can how the output can be processed. So,
the LLM is able to take natural language
queries from users
uh and able to determine which function
to call,
uh hence the name of this cool app
function calling. And um and is able to
um
then take and formulate those parameters
uh and extract the parameters from the
user
prompt and call them accordingly. So
important that LM should be able to
understand what the function is capable
of accepting and how to use this output
and what
what each parameter stands for.
Now we provide three key pieces of
functionality here, three functions.
One function is to list the tables in
the database,
then describing the table as well as
executing a query. By using these three
functions, the the chat
chatbot or the interface can easily
understand, okay, given this natural
language query by the user, I need to
see which table is the most relevant or
which tables are the most relevant. Then
see what information the table contains,
see the various columns in the table,
etc. And then what do I need to get out
of the table? What information do I need
to execute against the table at the
query and this is the three interfaces
we provide the um
provide the large language model and
this
allowing us to make this
application possible.
Now so we define these three functions.
One is to list all the tables to see
what kind of tables we have
in the in the database and then we
describe the describe table which
describe basically the table schema
such as like
what kind of fields do we have in each
of the tables and then we provide an
interface to the large language model by
defining a function for executing SQL
queries against that
against a given table.
For example,
an example statement could be select all
products of all from product table.
Now that we have
synthetic
table
multiple tables created in the in memory
database, we have the various interfaces
functions defined which can interact
with these tables, it's now time to
implement the function call. Function
calls
and
and in this part of the
in this part of the
collab we'll be directly allowing Gemini
to make those function calls
behind the scene and get the response
and kind of look at what the user is
asking for and use the information
provided by the response to formulate a
natural language response back to the
user. However, uh
given that these function calls interact
with the with the database
and LLMs are not perfect, they can
hallucinate. So, it's it's in a
production grade application you might
want to put safety
checks or even
have the code for
the queries checked manually by a human
before they're executed. For this demo,
we'll be letting we'll be letting the
LLM execute the function calls and
function use the function responses
automatically without any check in
between.
So, we then defined instruction for our
agent which will be saying, "Okay,
you're a helpful helpful chatbot. You
you have to answer the user's questions
by using the three kind of tools, the
database interaction tools which are the
three functions, list tables, describe
tables, and execute query
to provide the answer back to the user."
So, we are initializing the model,
providing it the tools here.
And because for complex queries it might
require multiple tries,
so we are
adding a retry mechanism here as well.
Now, everything is set up. So, hope
you're excited.
So, we asked the LLM use all the tools
at its disposal and tell us what is the
cheapest product in our
in in our whole database.
So, you can see that the LLM
first sees, okay, in order to figure out
what the cheapest product, let us look
at the various tables that is that are
present. And it finds a product table.
It then asks it It says, "Okay, now that
I have a product table, I need to know
what's inside it." So, it figures out,
okay, I would need to
like the agent figures out it needs to
dis-
get the column information to see if
there is a price
column somewhere, and there is, as as we
find earlier. And then it's okay, let's
Then it executes a query against that
table to get the the
and
gets the
cheapest product based on the price.
Um and then we ask
follow-up question of how much is it?
And then it
it has already access to the context
because we're using the chat interface
of the Gemini model, which keeps the
history of the previous interactions.
And if you remember from the one
the chat interface can kind of informs
the
informs this query here. It doesn't have
to retrieve the table information. It
directly executes a query
against that table, which it already
knows.
So, yeah, and
so and this this kind of
we can do it more often in the in the
collab, and you can understand what kind
of
information is it looking at when it's
defining
when it's interacting with with the
various functions. And And this part of
the collab kind of dives into more
detail around this. Um yeah.
So, in interest of time,
since our next collab is quite large,
I will go dive into it in a bit more
detail.
I I said I dive into this one in a bit
more detail, but the next one I'll be
skimming over some of the
high-level components. So, let's start
right with it.
Um
Sorry. Uh yeah.
So, um this collab talks about building
an agent with LangGraph and the Gemini
API. And uh it it uses a lot of the
Yeah, components.
Um I think we're still seeing we might
still be seeing the first notebook. So,
uh so, if you're showing a second
notebook, uh you might want to switch
tabs.
Okay.
Uh okay. And um give me a second. Yeah.
No worries. I love function calling,
though. I I think it's one of the most
underappreciated
uh one of the most underappreciated ways
to interact with large language models.
So, love that you you walked through
that example.
Yeah, perfect. Thank you.
Yes, so I mean, the function calling is
not all. Um
in this notebook, uh we go through um uh
uh
uh uh we use an open-source library
called LangGraph it uh to go over uh how
to build a complete application uh with
back-and-forth interactions and so on
and so forth. However, this collab is
quite detailed and in the interest of
not extending our livestream too much,
I'll be covering the high-level concepts
behind it. And the you can always go
into the uh collab uh at your own
convenience, those of you who are
listening to this livestream, and and um
try more detail on how it works.
So,
let's get started. So, uh the key
concepts to understand this notebook and
uh is the the LangGraph uses um a graph
structure. And a graph structure is
basically um can consists of nodes and
edges. And a node basically represents
an action or step to be taken. Um so,
um
kind of like uh like when a human um
uh interacts with an AR chatbot, there
is like uh you switch over from humans
to chatbot like it's like a turn system
where you kind of the human starts and
the chatbot answers etc. And notice the
action like human response, chatbot
response, function calling uh these are
all actions and the edge represents the
transition.
Uh for example, whenever the transition
uh the chatbot answers the human
uh or the user uh then it's the user's
turn to kind of answer back. Then these
as these are all transitions which are
represented by edges.
I would It's it's it's it's a bit more
detailed, so I would recommend looking
into the LangGraph documentation to
understand this concept in a bit more
detail. Now, in the first part of the um
um
collab, we define the core instructions
which allow this uh allow uh at each
step the the it provides all the
information to to the chatbot to
understand uh what is the current
situation, what has been said, what are
the messages that have been exchanged,
um what is the order because we're
talking about a barista chatbot here um
where
uh where you'll be kind of interacting
uh with the barista bot which can place
orders for you, get information, etc.
So, to see what uh the status of the
customer's order is and if whether or
not the order is completed, so it needs
that information at each step in order
to kind of um uh inform itself on how to
interact and which functions to call and
tools to invoke. So, that's what this uh
initial um setup is about to provide it
an interface to which it can keep track.
And then we uh define the instructions
for the barista bot allowing it uh
various options like clearing orders,
taking orders, placing orders, etc.
Then in this the first part of the um
collab, we talk about a single-turn
chatbot, right? We just see okay, with a
single interaction with the user, how
can we um we uh we uh like add the nodes
and the edges required to uh interact
like a single turn interaction with the
user where the the chatbot introduces
itself and the user asks it something
and that's it.
We can see that it's uh
starts in the
uh this chatbot directly transitions to
a chatbot and later on in the later uh
second part of this, we see that uh it's
the
it takes a single human message and the
chatbot answers.
Now, uh this is all stuff which is
pretty simple to understand. Where it
gets a bit more tricky and very powerful
at the same time is when uh you want to
have an almost indefinite interaction
between the human and the chatbot until
a terminal state is achieved. Like let's
say in this case, if you remember
earlier, we defined a finished function
where we we know that the order is
confirmed and placed, that's when we
want the interaction to end.
Uh and this is what we do in the third
part um of the um
the collab where we kind of define uh we
go over um the necessary structure to
define a two-and-fro chat between um
human and a chatbot. Um and um
now this can be of course troublesome,
especially if you have
an infinite you need a way to terminate
the conversation. So, uh we add a
conditional edge which uh provides an
interface to uh terminate the
conversation if the user um
like kind of has finished placing an
order and uh you can see here in the
graph like we have this graph showing
that a chatbot can interact with a human
and back and forth until a human decides
to
um
terminate the interaction and then it uh
kind of ends the application.
So, I'm going over it at a high level
because there's a lot of things to
cover, but basically uh the rest of the
code lab is quite big. Uh but idea is
that it just uh adds function calling
um to the loop. Till now it was just
text interactions with the model,
uh but you can also, of course, provide
various functions like we looked in the
first code lab, define various tools um
uh
uh and uh and allow it to uh uh get menu
information um
uh from the from from dynamic or static
sources, uh allow it to um kind of place
the so the uh place the orders here um
through various tools, get the current
order information, and much more. Now,
in the interest of time, I'll be uh uh
I'll be closing this um
code lab overview with one last
statement
uh and one last
uh diagram, actually. So, towards the
end of the code lab, you see that
step-by-step we have iteratively built
up a system where um a chatbot uh
chatbot is interacting with humans like
uh taking orders, um getting uh
retrieving providing the humans
necessary information, as well as
whenever necessary, it's invoking
various tools, and uh
uh and also doing function calling
behind the scenes
uh uh in order to um kind of complete
this application. And both the human and
the chatbot bot are able to then
terminate the application. So, this is
what uh
uh this code lab is about. I would
recommend going through it more detailed
to uh to get uh more information about
uh this and play around. There's a lot
more in store.
Thank you.
Awesome. Thank you so much for giving
that great overview over uh function
calling and LangGraph and how you can
kind of orchestrate models with things
like retrieval uh retrieval actions or
looking up tables in a database or
adding things to a database. Um as I
mentioned, I think this is one of the
most underexplored
and sort of high-impact, high-ROI things
that you can do with large language
models. Uh and it's really, really cool
to see all of it kind of laid out for
people to learn and to understand in
these collab notebooks. Thank you again
to Mark McDonald for creating them uh
and for making sure that they're
incorporated into this Kaggle course. Um
now I'm going to go back to our slide
deck.
Uh and it looks like up next we have our
Q&A. Um so I am so excited to welcome
all of our great subject matter experts
here today. Um but before I do that, I
want to give a quick shout-out and thank
you to all of our wonderful moderators
on the Discord channel um who are
answering questions tirelessly around
the clock, around the world. Um the sun
never really sets on generative AI at
Google. Um so thank you to Polong, Cass,
Mark, Eric, Irwin, and Miles um for for
kind of stepping in and for helping
helping debug things in real time. Um
and also make sure to add your own
questions to the Discord channel um so
that we can get our
guest speakers for tomorrow um to answer
to answer those items for you as well.
Um today um I'd like to I am honored and
and really excited to welcome our expert
host Steven uh Steven Johnson who is the
the creator of NotebookLM, Wes Dyer
who's the engineering lead for Ada team
which is focused on AI
uh kind of AI developer assistance and
more for
for for many of our Google products. Um
Julia,
Alan, and Patrick who are kind of
leading the charge for developing AI
features related to agents and function
calling on Google Cloud. Uh and uh have
a great list of questions in store for
you as well. Um so first off, Stephen,
uh welcome to the Generative AI
intensive course. We're really excited
to have you here. And also,
congratulations on winning, I believe
it's one of Time's products of the year
for NotebookLM. Is that correct? Yes. Uh
one of Time's inventions of the year. Uh
we were very excited. We got that just
happened a couple of weeks ago. So,
that's been really fun.
Excellent. And you were also at Ted AI
San Francisco, I believe, as as one of
the uh one of the guest speakers kind of
articulating some of the ways that
NotebookLM has been impactful and kind
of driving change
um in the in the Generative AI space. I
love how it's created kind of a new
paradigm that isn't just the the regular
old chatbot paradigm
um for for people to interact with these
models.
Yeah, that's part of the vision from
from the very start. I mean, we've been
working on what became NotebookLM for
more than 2 years now. And
the idea was like, what would happen if
you if you started from scratch um to
build a a tool for thinking and
organizing your ideas and organizing
your research and and potentially
writing
if you knew from the beginning that
there was going to be a state-of-the-art
language model at the center of the
product. Like, not not not adding it to
an existing product, but like start from
scratch with the idea of the whole thing
is going to be built around this this
incredible new technology. And and so,
that's that's what we ended up building.
And we kind of uh the way we've kind of
come to describe it is it's basically a
tool for understanding text.
Um Everything in the product is designed
to help you understand complex material,
organize ideas, extract insights, see
patterns.
And from the beginning, it was
predicated on the idea of what we call
source grounding, which is sometimes
called rag um in the industry. We we
think source grounding is a nicer term
for it. But it means that you upload the
sources, the information, the documents
that you need to do your work. Um
and then from that point on, all your
interactions with the model are grounded
in the information in those documents.
And so we go through and we have things
like inline citations. So when you get
an answer from the model, you see all
those answers have little kind of
footnotes and you can click directly on
those footnotes and see the original
passage in your sources that the model
used to come up with that answer, which
means that you can fact-check, you can
dive deeper and read the original source
material. Um,
it's just a really great way to navigate
through information that was just not
possible before. And all of this
is
is dependent on this incredible model of
Gemini Pro 1.5. Um, both the ability to
have that long context where we can put
all your documents in the context window
of the model,
um, and also things like citations which
Gemini does kind of natively.
Awesome. I love being able to to
understand like very discreetly how
longer context can really enable these
features for creators. Um, and and I
know many folks,
uh, many of the kind of developers that
I've talked to have mentioned that they
get frustrated sometimes where it can be
really challenging to figure out if if a
large language model is hallucinating
something or if it's actually referring
back to content. Um, so having having
those citations baked in is is really
compelling. Um, excellent. So so tell me
also a little bit about what has been
your favorite use case for Notebook LM
that you've seen, um, either within
Google or outside of Google. Yeah, I
mean, the thing that has been amazing
for me personally is I have a single
notebook, um, where I I have collected
as sources 8,000 quotes from books that
I've read over the years and articles
that I read over the years that I've
I've been kind of part of my research
and things like that. And plus I I write
books in my non-Google life and so I
also have the text of a lot of the books
that I've written in a single notebook.
So, you can have like 25 million words
worth of sources in a single notebook.
And so, when I when I go to this
notebook that has all these quotes and
has all this material that I've written,
I can just, you know, kind of riff on
ideas or ask questions, and then the
notebook the AI that's in that notebook
basically has
an incredible expertise in the history
of my thinking. Like, 20 years of my
thinking is kind of active in that
notebook. And so, whenever I'm like
wrestling with a new idea, I go to that
notebook and I'm like, "Hey, what do you
think of this? Any Any sparks? Any
connections?" And it'll be like, "Oh,
yeah, you read a book about this like 7
years ago that you've totally forgotten,
Stephen. And here is the excerpts from
it. Here's what's relevant to to it, you
know?" So, it feels like an extension of
of my brain in this way that is really
powerful. So, that's
that's been really exciting. And then we
can talk about you know, we released
this new audio overviews feature
that came out
2 months ago or so, and that's where you
upload your sources,
and you generate a kind of remarkably
lifelike podcast-style conversation
between two hosts. There's another
version of this at Google called
Illuminate, which is I believe what I've
been used to generate the podcasts for
for this for this course.
And people are just loving that feature.
And the craziest use case for that is
that we that we've seen a lot of people
do is you upload your resume,
and you generate a an audio overview
based on your resume. And the And the
hosts are basically instructed to be
engaging and enthusiastic about whatever
you give them. And so,
it's a great way to feel good about
yourself
cuz you'll upload your resume, and
they'll be like, "Wow, Stephen, you
really had a very busy year. You've
accomplished so many things."
Excellent. I love I love having that
personal that personal hype hype
notebook to to be uh to be celebrating
all of the great successes. This is
wonderful and uh the the idea that you
mentioned around having kind of like a a
thought partner
um that uh
that's basically that's basically you
just you with perfect uh perfect memory
like perfect recall for all of the the
different bits of information that
you've experienced over the last years.
That's super super cool. Um I and really
really excited to play more. Uh if folks
are are interested in in testing out
Notebook LM, uh what is the URL that
they should go to? At
notebooklm.google.com.
Excellent. Thank you so much. And
speaking of having kind of a a
personalized uh
a personalized hyper expert uh sort of
companion for doing work, um Wes, uh I
have been really really uh enchanted
with the AI features that you and your
team have been baking into Colab. I use
it literally every day both for code
generation as well as fixing errors and
explaining errors. Um so thank you thank
you so much for your work and then
welcome also to the to the Kaggle
generative AI intensive course.
Thank you. Yeah, we use it we use it
every day, too, as we build out more and
more Colab features. Um
Colab uh and and data science agent is
uh just have been really a benefit for
all of us. One thing to kind of note is
that the data science agent for Colab
that we announced back in May at IO um
was uh is just the latest in a string of
AI kind of enhancements to Colab. And
all of these things really kind of do
the thing same thing, which is that they
increase the velocity that all of us can
uh move at when using AI tools um
while in doing development in Colab and
other places.
With more velocity, of course, means we
can experiment faster, try out more
ideas. And we found as we're doing our
own kind of AI, ML, and data science
work that the that the primary
determining factor about how much we can
do and how much progress we make is with
the velocity of the experimentation we
can have.
And so, enhancing people's ability to do
to to have more velocity by giving them
tools like the AI features,
um is really kind of magnifies what they
can do.
And specifically for the data science
agent, uh what we announced back in in
May was that uh is that you can kind of
ask a question, give a data set, or even
ask like a modeling question, and uh of
the agent, it'll go off into a
multi-step process, including things
like importing the data, exploring the
data, cleaning the data, visualizing it,
and ultimately ending up with answers to
questions, as well as um models and that
kind of thing as the output. Then from
there, you can iterate and kind of go on
to do bigger and better things. We're
continuing to enhance this and and bring
out new ways for people to interact with
it.
Excellent. And and I'm assuming behind
the scenes these agents are using tools
like function calling, um and and all of
the great kind of uh the great features
that we learned about during the the
course of this last lesson. Is that
correct? That is absolutely correct. We
use function calling, we use retrieval,
all kinds of wonderful things that we've
been talking about.
Excellent. That's that's perfect. Uh and
and I am very very excited to hear that
more and more AI features are going to
be coming to Colab. I know that it has
uh increased my velocity personally
uh uh you know, magnitudes over the
course of the last 6 months. Uh so, I'm
excited to see the the next features get
released. Um and the next question would
be for both Steven and West. Uh we
already touched on this a little bit,
but uh how are you thinking about
function calling and retrieval in the
systems that you're building? Are these
techniques and tools that that are being
used? It sounds like they are for data
science agents. Um Steven, are for is
retrieval getting used within Notebook
LM? Is that Is that one of the things
that that's kind of baked into the to
the citations process or the the data
recalling process?
Uh yeah, I mean, it's a little bit above
my technical pay grade to get into the
details of this, but but yes, we do I
mean, we do this kind of semantic
retrieval. Um that's an important part
of the process. Um particularly if you
have a large set of sources that exceed
the amount of information that can fit
in the
model's context. And so, there's a you
know, we've we've built some quite smart
tools for kind of getting the most
relevant passages from your sources um
and then putting them in front of the
model with the custom prompt that we
have. Um
And so, that's that's been something
that was literally like the first
feature we had um
back in the day. It kind of it it was
just in a Colab, basically in in August
of 2022.
Um you could give it some source
material and ask some questions, but the
source material could be like a page
long instead of, you know, 25 million
words. So, we've made a little bit of
progress.
Amazing. Like I I love that the the kind
of fundamental Lego brick uh building
blocks that that folks are learning this
week are are the same tools and
techniques that folks are using to build
the products at Google and then also
external to Google. Um this is very
exciting. Thank you thank you both uh
uh for for the great discussion uh and
for uh for building the the products
that they all are sharing. Um we'll have
links in the the YouTube videos as well
for folks if they want to go and try out
uh try out Notebook LM and then also try
out the AI assistant features in Colab.
Um
Next question. Uh this is for Patrick
and Julia. Have you seen any major
changes to agent compositions in
production since you started writing the
white paper? Um and I and thank you also
for authoring the white papers that
folks have been reading um over the
course of this last day. What's changed,
what's stayed the same, and then what
are the challenges and opportunities you
see kind of the new exciting things
coming down the road?
Yeah, for sure. I'll start off on that
one. So, you know, thanks for having us
today. You know, it's it's interesting,
you know, Julie and I have been thinking
about agents for a really really long
time, you know,
way before the GenAI, you know, kind of
craze took took foot in the world. You
know, Julia was working on things like
cognitive architectures and and trying
to, you know, do research on that and
understand how could we implement these
things in production and and I was also
working on sort of like the precursor to
generative AI agents and just the
conversational AI space and natural
language processing and stuff like that.
So, when we started writing this paper,
you know, it's obviously it's really
hard to predict the future in this space
and know like what's going to come in
the next 3 months or 6 months because in
the GenAI space that's kind of like an
eternity, right?
So, as we thought about, you know,
putting, you know, words to paper and
thinking about what are the ways that
people will start kind of architecting
these agents in the future, we thought
really carefully about like what are the
composition of agents going to look
like? What's you know, what's going to
happen a month from now? What's going to
happen 6 months from now? You know,
things like that. And so, I think the
things that have stayed the same roughly
are the architectures. You know, we see
that, you know, agents have models,
agents at the foundation, you know, they
have tools that they have access to and
then these, you know, kind of
orchestration layers, runtimes,
memory,
goals to try to achieve these particular
things. So, a lot of that has really
stayed the same and I think we're happy
to see that the paper has aged well as
as we've kind of written it and has as
things have, you know, grown over time.
The things that have really changed, I
think, are the fact that the models
themselves are just simply getting
better and better over time. You know,
when we first started writing the paper,
we had some really early LLMs and, you
know, they were okayish, but it ended
up, you know, you had to put a lot more
into your reasoning layer and your logic
layer to kind of control the things that
you wanted your model to do. Uh but with
some of the latest models that are
coming out, it really just makes the
orchestration layer so much more simple.
Uh a lot of these models are baked in
with much better tool calling, uh much
better logic and reasoning uh abilities
to do chain of thought natively,
abilities to do, you know, code
execution natively. And so, all of that
is really just making um sort of like
the higher-level abstractions of
building these agent frameworks even,
you know, easier and easier over time.
So, I don't know, Julie, if you want to
add anything to that.
Yeah, absolutely. I'm so big plus one to
everything that, you know, Patrick has
said. We've really been thinking about
this for a while. And um I'm loving
hearing all the shout-outs to um
function calling and to tool use today
um because that's, you know, been
something I've been thinking about for
for quite a long time. So, really
excited also to see what folks start to
build with uh the contents of the of
this course. And I think that's a little
bit what I'd love to focus on here on on
the challenges and opportunities side
that we see. I think um there's still so
much that can happen here in this space.
Right now, you know, we still see, I
would say them I would call them fairly
simple implementations, often with rag,
with a handful of APIs, things like
that. And what I'm starting to see and
what I'm really excited about is the
ability to solve kind of complex
real-world problems with lots of
different APIs, with mutating actions,
with running different simulations, etc.
And I think there's just so many
industries that this can apply to and
also that it goes far beyond the realm
of just chat implementations per se. And
And there's so much more that you can
you can start to do with these things if
you think about industries like supply
chain or security or kind of other
spaces that um
that really have kind of background
processes that can also work and work
and automate and and when you hear
things like what Notebook LM is thinking
about also going outside of that kind of
frame and interaction.
Awesome. Thank you both so much and
thank you for the great work that you've
been doing to build robust function
calling and tools used into the the
Vertex AI Gemini APIs. I know we've also
been drawing on some of those learnings
for the Gemini developer APIs. Um so
thank you thank you for making it real.
Um and Julia, has anyone you know
speaking of specialized domains and
specialized kind of versions of function
calling and tools used, has anyone
implemented an agent focused on
security?
Um
and where can I find overall guidance on
implementing agents for cybersecurity?
That's a great question and as I just
mentioned, the security industry is a
space where there's a lot of
opportunities for agents. I mean just
think about things like that
classification tracking
etc. and I really think that a lot of
this is just at the beginning. So as far
as I know, we'll actually be talking
about SecLM tomorrow. So look forward to
tomorrow's sessions where we'll look
into I think a semi-auto semi-agentic
setup that can address some of those
security challenges using using LLMs. So
more to come on that front.
Excellent. Excited to have the
discussion tomorrow.
Um and also is there a way to evaluate
the accuracy of the tools that Gemini
selects? Are there
deviations whenever Gemini
selects a tool? Are there any ways to
remediate?
And I I've run into this at least a
couple of times where
when I when I specify different
functions or different tools to call,
sometimes multiple tools might be
applicable to the same problem.
How can you start thinking about
doing
kind of composite tool selection or or
just
getting additional information from the
user before selecting a tool.
Yeah, absolutely. And I absolutely love
this question because and it's something
that Patrick and I spent a lot of time
thinking about also as we wrote the
paper. I think there's an entire
follow-up section to do on kind of
evaluation and taking these things from
kind of testing to to kind of production
and and and iterating on each of these
these tools.
From that perspective right now, I'd
love to kind of just do a quick
shout-out to actually some of the Vertex
AI tooling that we have around
evaluation. So, anybody that's working
kind of with function calling, you can
actually check out the Gen AI evaluation
service and using kind of your
prototype, you can upload data and
actually test kind of and evaluate
outcomes to kind of get a sense of the
accuracy and those kind of things ahead
of time and start to see how you can
kind of fiddle with the with the
different knobs and dials in order to
kind of make these things more accurate.
So, I think folks will will follow up
with a link on on that front. With
regards to function calling now, like
specifically, I think that there are a
couple things that are pretty generic to
Gen AI as a whole.
You want to log and analyze kind of tool
selection decisions over time. So, you
want to track Gemini's choices for
tools, their user queries, and then
understand kind of the rationale and the
patterns behind those things so that you
can start to work and and improve those
kind of potential errors.
And and then at the same time that ties
directly into developing kind of those
test cases with a diverse set of
queries. So, as with any Gen AI product,
you really want to kind of get those use
cases, get those testers, get those
people that are are starting to use
whatever you're building so you can see
how they're using it and and collect
where Gemini's also failing or where
there's kind of issues with the with the
tool call so that you can then use those
things to over time do things like
refine the the prompt engineering.
We've had all different kinds of
examples where
you you have to be really careful with
the wording that you use in in the
prompt that you're putting inside,
right? We've we've seen
seen examples where essentially without
meaning to
we actually told the model not to use
functions. And
and so we we we just have to be really
really careful and and by like
collecting those examples we can then
actually look for those patterns and
look to understand kind of what the the
model is doing.
Secondly, we can obviously work on
expanding and continuing to improve the
tool definitions. So ensuring that
they're really unambiguous and actually
often using the model to help you help
you do these things is is really useful.
And
over time you can also as you especially
think about getting to production you
can also think about things like
doing targeted learning where you're
kind of fine-tuning Gemini or really
giving it
a rag-based query on a tool example
ahead of time
so that it knows a bit better as to what
it should be doing in in in in this
case. So I think there's there's there's
definitely some opportunities there and
it's going to continue to kind of
improve as as the models also continue
to improve.
Yeah, I love that and I I really do feel
like you can you can get a lot of you
can get a lot of alpha just by investing
a lot in prompt engineering at least
today
and helping
using Gemini or using other models to
help build the prompt to to have more
robust systems. If folks are interested
in open-source options for
for evaluations as well, Um, uh, been
really loving using PromptFoo, which is
an open-source evaluations option
um that supports both text, code, and
and multi-modal based evaluations. So,
we'll have the link for that in the in
the chat as well.
Um, excellent. And then, yeah.
sorry, Paige. I just wanted to jump in
real quick and and add a a comment about
evaluations. Um, if you are watching
this and you're curious of more about
evaluations, we're going to be covering
this on day five in our ML Ops section
of the same course. So, join us in a
couple of days and we'll we'll touch
more on evaluations as well.
Excellent. And, uh,
moving just a little bit cuz,
uh, one of the fun things about Google
offices is that to conserve energy, if
you don't move enough, uh, the lights go
off in the back of the office. So, if
you see me moving around, um, that is
why. Excellent. Thank you for calling it
out and, uh, get excited for day number
five where we'll be discussing
evaluations in more depth.
Um, and then, next question, uh, in
building an agentic RAG system for
better responses, there are a lot of
intermediate steps between the user
query and getting a response from the
large language model. How can we deal
with that latency? Um, Patrick and
Allen, do you want to take this one?
Sure. Yeah. Um, I mean, I think that,
uh,
don't forget about traditional
application development best practices.
You can invest in pre-processing,
improving the quality of the data,
improving the chunking mechanisms or
whatever the details are for your data,
and then,
uh, improving the quality and
performance of the search, right?
Because RAG or, uh,
grounding is really all about getting
the right facts or chunks into the
context window of the prompt. So, you
can invest a lot in the system,
when you're going to agentic RAG, you're
basically adding more and more steps.
Perhaps reducing those steps through,
uh, that investment is is sort of
standard application
uh, best practices.
Um
additionally, you can do tricks like
execute multiple queries in parallel and
you can evaluate the responses of those
parallel queries and pick the most
relevant answers.
Uh there's some other stuff. Patrick,
we've talked about this a bunch. Do you
want to jump in? Yeah, I I think just to
add to this, you know, from a developer
perspective, there's always this
propensity to want to use the the
coolest, fanciest,
you know, kind of code or
implementations out there. But a lot of
times, you know, going back to kind of
just basic system design principles and
thinking about simplicity is really the
right way to go. And I know generative
AI right now is super cool and agents
are cool and rag is cool.
But sometimes just doing, you know,
retrieval from a cache and responding
with an answer is the best actual the
best outcome because you have to
remember that when you're building these
systems for production,
what really matters is the outcome,
right? Like the results that you're
trying to achieve. It doesn't matter
that you implemented the coolest, most
agentic system behind the the scenes,
you know, what matters is the outcome to
the users of that system. And so kind of
keep those things in mind as you're
doing this, you know, traditional system
design thinking around how you should be
implementing this for your your
customers, your partners, or for
yourself.
Mhm. Can I do one more quick plug? You
mentioned cash. A lot of people are
talking about caching the final output
and that's awesome, right? Um context
cash is an unsung hero. A lot of people
are not experimenting with that enough.
Go check out long context window and
context cash.
You can get a lot of stuff done for
especially for small use cases or early
prototypes.
There's a lot of
opportunity in those features. And then
we covered context caching as well as
some of the optimization step for
retrieval and making LLMs faster in our
day one and two. So go read those white
papers, those of you listening, for more
information.
Excellent. And I love the I love the
call out as well to use whatever tool is
most appropriate for the task, even if
it isn't necessarily like the most
bleeding edge generative AI tool.
Um I've I've often been using function
calling for calling smaller open-source
fine-tuned models um to do specialized
things like image segmentation
um or or kind of more dedicated tasks.
And given that they're much smaller
models, they're located on device, um
they can uh they can get much faster
results than if you were if you were
using a much more powerful model. Um uh
and also often for cheaper. So, so
function calling
uh it has been a really nice win for
helping right-size calls to the to the
right tools.
Awesome. Page, maybe just one quick
throw in there. We've also seen it with
calling like time series forecasting
models. Um
which gets really, really interesting
when you can get that kind of a time
series forecast into kind of whatever
system you're you're starting to use and
things like that. So, we're
going to plus one on that front.
Excellent. Very cool. And and so, last
question um before we get into our pop
quiz, um uh this is for Alan. When would
you recommend using a minimal
implementation like the Gemini API um
versus a stateful graph-based approach
like using LangGraph, um which is an
open-source library that we were using
in the code lab?
Sure.
Um
this is sort of what we were talking
about before. These are just design
principles, right? Um
are you doing a quick prototype? Uh
please, just start quick. Like just get
some ideas out there, play with the
tools, learn the tools, see what's
capable, see if your use case works out.
Um
the lowest number of dependencies, just
just get in there and play.
But, uh it is difficult to control
agentic systems. Uh and especially as
the complexity grows
your level of effort to control that
system
grows.
So,
um
I I think maybe day one just use the
SDK, play around, and get going.
Probably day two get invested in some
kind of a system to control that
behavior.
Um I do like LangGraph or graph-based
representations. It's not the only one,
there's lots of other frameworks out
there that use graph-based
representations. BradBoard is a great
one um that uses graph as config as
opposed to a graph implemented in code.
Both of these are just means of
understanding what the agent is capable
of doing. That's like introspection,
what might happen and observability,
what did the agent do? What choices,
what steps did it make, etc. These are
really tools to help you as a developer
understand what's happening and control
what's happening. That That's all it is.
So, these are These are techniques that
have been created to help you as a
developer better understand the system
that you're building and better control
it. That's it. So, I I do think play
around first.
Um you don't have to invest in a system.
But adopting a system on day two is
probably a good plan because by day 20
you will wish that you had done so.
Yeah.
Um
Excellent. And there
and there are many great open-source
libraries um being created to help with
precisely these uh precisely these
problems. Things like Crew AI and Agent
Ops and LangGraph. Um I think there are
GenKit, yeah. Lots and lots of uh lots
and lots of things to to help bring uh
uh to bring reason to the chaos. So uh
so excited to see even more of these get
built out and become more robust over
time.
Um awesome. Thank you all so much for uh
for our experts uh for giving your time,
for uh your insights, and then also for
writing all of the great curriculum and
white papers that we've been learning
from these past uh these past days. Um
really appreciate you and your time.
Uh and thank you thank you again. This
has been fantastic. Um and now, uh
without further ado, uh we are going
into the pop quiz. So, everyone get
pens, pencils, papers, something to
write down uh your answers on. Uh uh and
we will have six questions today. Um I
will go ahead and get started with the
first. What is a generative agent? Is it
A, a type of machine learning model? B,
an application that can observe the
world and act upon it using tools? C, an
LLM that can only be used for text
generation? Or D, a kind of hardware for
training large language models? Um
hopefully everybody was reading the
material um and can uh and pick out the
right answer pretty quickly, but I'm
going to give you five,
four,
three, two,
one. Hopefully everybody picked B, an
application that can observe the world
and act upon it using tools and function
calling. Um Question number two. What is
the primary function of the
orchestration layer in a generative AI
agent? Um Is it A, to generate creative
text and images? B, to manage the
agent's internal reasoning and planning
process?
C, to interact with users through a
conversational interface? Or D, to store
and retrieve data from external sources?
Um hopefully everybody was paying
attention in the white papers. I believe
this might have also been mentioned in
some of our code labs.
Um but I'm going to give you five,
four,
three,
two,
one.
Hopefully everybody picked B, a way to
manage the agent's internal reasoning
and planning process.
Number three. Um in what scenario might
a developer choose
to use functions over extensions in a
generative AI agent? Um, is it A, when
the agent needs to make multiple API
calls in a sequence? B, when the API
requires real-time interaction with the
agent? C, when the developer needs more
control over the data flow and API
execution? Or D, when the API is easily
accessible by the agent's
infrastructure? Um, hopefully everybody
was paying attention in the white
papers.
Um, make sure to jot down your answer.
And it is C, when the developer needs
more control over the data flow and API
execution. Um, question number four,
we're halfway there. What is the purpose
of data stores in a generative AI agent?
Um, is it A, to store the agent's
configuration settings and parameters?
B, to provide the agent with access to
dynamic and up-to-date information? C,
to execute complex calculations and data
transformations? Or D, to monitor and
evaluate the agent's performance over
time?
I'll give you five,
four,
three,
two, one. And it is B, to provide the
agent with access to dynamic and
up-to-date information. You know, we
were discussing that quite a bit
yesterday and also today. All of these
retrieval processes are very, very
important for making sure the agents get
the right answers. Um, and all of also
that our machine learning systems are
equipped with the right data to give you
the most up-to-date answers.
Question number five, which of the
following is not a characteristic
typically associated with generative AI
agents? Is it A, they can create new
content such as text, images, or music?
B, they can learn from large data sets
to identify patterns and generate
similar content? C, they possess
inherent consciousness and understanding
of the content they create? Or D, they
can be used for tasks like translation,
summarization, and content creation,
which is not a characteristic typically
associated with generative AI agents.
Five,
four,
three,
two,
one,
C. Agents do not possess inherent
consciousness and understanding of the
content they create. They are just
acting on acting on inputs and outputs,
not in a conscious or or
self-deterministic way.
Um and then last question, number six.
What is the mixture of agent experts
approach in agent development? Um is it
A, combining multiple language models
with a single agent? B, using a variety
of tools to enhance agent capabilities?
C, combining specialized agents, each
excelling in a particular domain or
task? Or D, integrating different
reasoning frameworks within the
orchestration layer?
Five, four, three, two,
one,
the answer is C, combining specialized
agents, each excelling in a particular
domain or task. And you might have also
heard of agent mixture models, um or
mixture of expert models rather, um that
are that are
sort of doing similar sorts of things.
That are that are baking together
many different models, each each a
little bit better at particular domains
or tasks. Um so hopefully everybody got
100% correct. If not, make sure to refer
back to the white papers and the the
different assets that we were using
um throughout the week so that you can
uh you can learn and reflect. Um and I
want to thank you everyone again for
taking the time to to learn today and
with us over this 5-day adventure. Um
make sure to tune in tomorrow where
we'll be talking about domain-specific
large language models and bringing on
another great great round of guest
speakers uh and learning a lot more
about PsychLM and some of the other
domain-specific models that Julia was
mentioning earlier. Um so thank you
again, and we will see you tomorrow.